We present Video Pose Distillation for Few-Shot, Fine-Grained Action Recognition.
This work is a collaboration between Adobe Research and Stanford University.
Human centric sports represent a large class of interesting activities
where large amounts of video data are available and where athletes
perform a sophisticated set of acrobatic feats and technical actions.
Performing tasks such as recognizing, detecting or retrieving
these actions is an exciting area of research,
and choosing the right feature representations is important.
For video centered around athletes and their motion, pose-based methods
leverage information about the human body, but they depend on accurate 2D pose estimation.
This is problematic, because sports video is challenging for pose estimation.
Motion is often most intense in the critical action
frames, causing blur and ambiguity.
Athletes also undertake extreme poses, seldom seen in daily life.
Improving pose estimation is possible, but requires new pose
annotations, which can be expensive to obtain.
By contrast, end-to-end
learning, for tasks such as action recognition, is often preferred.
By training on the pixels
directly, circumventing pose, these methods can be more reliable,
even if pose estimates are not, but they require more labeled
actions to train and are specialized to a particular task.
This motivates the question:
How do we learn reliable
pose features for sports video that, like pose,
benefit a variety of downstream tasks?
And how do we do so without new pose annotations?
We introduce Video Pose Distillation, or VPD, a novel method that combines
the benefits of both pose and end-to-end methods.
The inputs to VPD are an unlabeled corpus of video
and a pose feature extraction pipeline, in this case
consisting of a pretrained pose estimator and view-invariant pose embedding.
Given each input video to VPD,
there are two data pathways, the teacher and the student.
The teacher takes the video and extracts
pose features for the athlete using pretrained models.
The student is a neural network that is distilled
on the pixels, with the teacher’s outputs as weak-supervision.
This setup is beneficial in several ways.
First, note that no ground truth pose or action
labels are required for distillation.
VPD is agnostic to downstream tasks.
Our key insight is that, by training the student
over a large corpus of unlabeled video, the student learns features
that agree with the teacher’s pose when the teacher is reliable.
And, the student, with access to the pixels, is able
to specialize to the visual patterns in the sport video domain
and avoid the teacher’s mistakes when the teacher is unreliable.
We also leverage temporal information, from video, to learn motion.
This is done by encoding both the current frame and the previous
frame with the teacher to obtain the current pose and its temporal derivative.
The student receives the pixels and optical flow of the current frame
and is tasked to produce a descriptor.
A second network, to decode the student’s
features, is used at training time to provide supervision for the student.
This decoder has the added effect of allowing the student to produce features that differ from the teacher,
encapsulating motion information as well as pose.
At inference time, only the student is needed to produce features for downstream tasks.
We find that VPD features outperform their teacher on fine-grained action
recognition tasks on our four evaluation datasets
when used as inputs to a generic GRU classifier.
They also outperform or
are competitive with state-of-the-art pose-based and end-to-end methods.
In limited supervision settings, such as when only 8 to 64 examples
per action class are available, VPD features perform well.
Here are two datasets where pose estimation is the most challenging.
VPD significantly outperforms its teacher and prior methods.
Finally, VPD features are also effective for
tasks such as action retrieval and detection.
In summary, we have presented Video Pose Distillation,
a novel method to learn robust pose
features for challenging video datasets, without new pose labels,
that combines the benefits of both pose and end-to-end learning.
As a potential application of VPD, we hope that our work will improve
analysis of interesting sports datasets
and be beneficial for tasks such as labeling and curating new ones.
Thank you for listening.
Please check out our paper for additional experiments and details.
Our code and data are also available at our website.